<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Heere beginneth a mery iest of Dank Hew munk of Leicestre, and how he was foure times slain and once hanged</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1560</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13257</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119036</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854243</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854243</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19652</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03127)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19652)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1070:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Heere beginneth a mery iest of Dank Hew munk of Leicestre, and how he was foure times slain and once hanged</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>At the long Shop adioyning vnto Saint Mildreds Churche in the Pultrie, by Iohn Alde],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1560?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A chap book.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon. Suggested publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dane Hew (Legendary character) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:19652:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:19652:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <head>¶ Heere beginneth a <hi>mery I eſt of Dan<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hew Munk of</hi> Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtre, and how he was foure times ſlain and once hanged.</head>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19652:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N olde time there was in Leceſter town</l>
            <l>An Abbay of Munks of great renown</l>
            <l>As ye ſhall now after heer</l>
            <l>But amongſt them all was one there</l>
            <l>That paſſed all his Brethern iwis</l>
            <l>His name was Dane Hew ſo haue I blis</l>
            <l>This Munk was yung and luſty</l>
            <l>And to fair women he had a fanſy</l>
            <l>And for them he laid great wait in deed</l>
            <l>In Leiceſter dwelled a Tayler I reed</l>
            <l>Which wedded a woman fair and good</l>
            <l>they looued eche other by my hood</l>
            <l>Seuen yeer and ſomwhat more</l>
            <l>Dane Hew looued this taylers Wife ſore,</l>
            <l>And thought alway in his minde</l>
            <l>When he might her alone finde</l>
            <l>And how he might her aſſay</l>
            <l>And if ſhe would not to ſay him nay</l>
            <l>Vpon a day he ſaid fair woman free</l>
            <l>without I haue my pleaſure of thee</l>
            <l>I am like to go from my wit</l>
            <l>Sir ſhe ſaid I haue many a ſhrewd fit</l>
            <l>Of my huſband euery day,</l>
            <l>Dame he ſaid / ſay not nay</l>
            <l>My pleaſure I muſt haue of thee</l>
            <l>what ſo euer that it coſt mee</l>
            <l>She anſwered and ſaid if it muſt needs be</l>
            <l>Come to morow vnto me</l>
            <l>For then my huſband rideth out of the town</l>
            <l>and then to your wil I wil be bown</l>
            <l>And then we may make good game</l>
            <l>and if ye come not ye be to blame</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19652:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
But Dane Hew firſt tel thou me</l>
            <l>What that my rewarde ſhalbe</l>
            <l>Dame he ſaid by my fay</l>
            <l>twenty nobles of good money</l>
            <l>For we wil make good cheer this day:</l>
            <l>And ſo they kiſt and went their way</l>
            <l>The tayler came home at euen tho</l>
            <l>Like as he was wunt to doo</l>
            <l>And his wife tolde him all and ſome</l>
            <l>How Dane Hew in the morning would come</l>
            <l>and what her meed of him ſhould be</l>
            <l>What? dame thou art mad ſo mot I thee</l>
            <l>Wilt thou me a Cuckolds hood giue?</l>
            <l>That ſhould me ſhrewdly greeue,</l>
            <l>Nay Sir ſhe ſaid, by ſweet ſaint Iohn</l>
            <l>I wil keep my ſelf a good woman</l>
            <l>And get thee money alſo iwis</l>
            <l>For he hath made therof a promiſſe</l>
            <l>To morow earely heer to be</l>
            <l>I know wel he wil not fail me</l>
            <l>And I ſhall lock you in the cheſt</l>
            <l>that ye out of the way may be milt</l>
            <l>And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dane Hew commeth hether early</l>
            <l>About fiue of the clock truely</l>
            <l>For at that time his houre is ſet</l>
            <l>to come hether then without any let</l>
            <l>Then I ſhall you call ful lightly</l>
            <l>Look that ye come vnto me quickly</l>
            <l>And when the day began to appeer in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning</l>
            <l>Dane Hew came thither warde faſt renning</l>
            <l>He thought that he had paſt his houre</l>
            <l>then ſoftly he knocked at the taylers door</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19652:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
She roſe vp and bad him come neer</l>
            <l>And ſaid Sir welcome be ye heer</l>
            <l>Good morow (he ſaid) gentle miſtris</l>
            <l>Now tel me where your huſband is</l>
            <l>That we may be ſure indeed</l>
            <l>Sir ſhe ſaid ſo God me ſpeed</l>
            <l>He is foorth of the town</l>
            <l>And wil not come home til after noon</l>
            <l>With that Dane Hew was wel content</l>
            <l>And lightly in armes he did her hent</l>
            <l>And thought to haue had good game</l>
            <l>Sir ſhe ſaid let be for ſhame</l>
            <l>For I wil knowe firſt what I ſhall haue</l>
            <l>For when I haue it I wil it not craue</l>
            <l>Giue me twenty Nobles firſt</l>
            <l>And doo with me then what ye liſt</l>
            <l>By my Preeſthood quoth he than</l>
            <l>thou ſhalt haue in Golde and ſiluer anon</l>
            <l>Thou ſhalt no longer craue it of me</l>
            <l>Lo my miſtreſſe where they be</l>
            <l>And in her lap he it threw</l>
            <l>Gramercy ſhe ſaid vnto Dane Hew</l>
            <l>Dane Hew thought this wife to aſſay</l>
            <l>abide ſir ſhe ſaid til I haue laid it away</l>
            <l>For ſo ſhe thought it ſhould be beſt</l>
            <l>With that ſhe opened then a Cheſt</l>
            <l>then Dane Hew thought to haue had her alone</l>
            <l>But the tayler out of the cheſt anon</l>
            <l>And ſaid ſir Munk if thou wilt ſtand</l>
            <l>I ſhall giue thee a ſtroke with my brand</l>
            <l>that thou ſhalt haue but little luſt vnto my wife</l>
            <l>And lightly without any more ſtrife</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19652:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
He hit Dane Hew vpon the hed</l>
            <l>That he fel down ſtark dead</l>
            <l>Thus was he firſt ſlain in deed</l>
            <l>Alas then ſaid his wife with an euil ſpeed</l>
            <l>Haue ye ſlain this munk ſo ſoone?</l>
            <l>Whither now ſhall we run or gone?</l>
            <l>There is no remedy then ſaid he</l>
            <l>without thou giue good counſail to me</l>
            <l>To conuay this falſe preeſt out of the way</l>
            <l>That no man ſpeak of it ne ſay</l>
            <l>That I haue killed him or ſlain</l>
            <l>Or els that we haue doon it in vain</l>
            <l>Yea ſit (ſhe ſaid) let him abide</l>
            <l>Til it be ſoon in the euen tide</l>
            <l>Then ſhall we him wel conuay</l>
            <l>For ye ſhall beare him into the Abbay</l>
            <l>And ſet him ſtraight vp by the wall</l>
            <l>and come your way foorth withall</l>
            <l>The Abbot ſought him all about</l>
            <l>For he heard ſay that he was out</l>
            <l>And was very angry with him in deed</l>
            <l>and would neuer reſt ſo God me ſpeed</l>
            <l>Vntil Dane Hew that he had found</l>
            <l>and bad his man to ſeek him round</l>
            <l>About the place, and to him ſay</l>
            <l>That he come ſpeak with me ſtraight way</l>
            <l>Foorth went his man til at the laſt</l>
            <l>Beeing abrode his eye he caſt</l>
            <l>Aſide: where he Dane Hew did ſee</l>
            <l>and vnto him then ſtraight went he</l>
            <l>And thinking him to be aliue</l>
            <l>He ſaid, Dane Hew ſo mut I thriue</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19652:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
I haue ſought you and meruel how</l>
            <l>that I could not finde you til now</l>
            <l>Dane Hew ſtood as ſtil as he that could not tel</l>
            <l>what he ſhould ſay, no more he did good nor il</l>
            <l>With that the Abbots man ſaid with good intent</l>
            <l>Sir ye muſt come to my Lord, or els you be ſhent</l>
            <l>When Dane Hew anſwered neuer a dele.</l>
            <l>He thought he would aſke ſome counſail</l>
            <l>Then to the Abbot he gan him hye</l>
            <l>I pray you my Lord come by and by</l>
            <l>And ſee where Dane Hew ſtands ſtraight by the wall</l>
            <l>and wil not anſwere what ſo euer I call</l>
            <l>And he ſtareth and looketh vpon one place</l>
            <l>Like a man that is out of grace</l>
            <l>And one woord he wil not ſpeak for me</l>
            <l>Get me a ſtaf (quoth the Abbot) and I ſhall ſee</l>
            <l>And if he ſhall not vnto me anſwere.</l>
            <l>Then when the Abbot came there</l>
            <l>And ſaw him ſtand vp right by the wall</l>
            <l>He then to him began to call</l>
            <l>And ſaid thou falſe Bribour thou ſhalt aby</l>
            <l>Why keepeſt thou not thy ſeruice truely</l>
            <l>Come hether he ſaid with an euil ſpeed</l>
            <l>But no woord that Dane Hew anſwered in deed</l>
            <l>what whorſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ꝙ the Abbot) why ſpekeſt not thou?</l>
            <l>Speak or els I make God avow</l>
            <l>I wil giue thee ſuch a ſtroke vpon thy head</l>
            <l>That I ſhall he gaue him ſuch a rap</l>
            <l>That he fel down at that clap</l>
            <l>Thus was he the ſecond time ſlain</l>
            <l>and yet he wroght them much more pain</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19652:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
As ye ſhall afterward heer ful wel</l>
            <l>Sir quoth the abbots an ye haue doon il</l>
            <l>For ye haue ſlain Dane Hew now</l>
            <l>And ſuſpended this place I make God a vow</l>
            <l>What remedy (quod the Abbot than?)</l>
            <l>Yes quoth his man by ſweet Saint Iohn</l>
            <l>If ye would me a good rewarde giue</l>
            <l>That I may be the better while that I liue</l>
            <l>Yes (ꝙ the Abbot) xl. ſhillings thou ſhalt haue</l>
            <l>And if thou can mine honor ſaue</l>
            <l>My Lord I tel you ſo mot I thee</l>
            <l>Vnto ſuch a Taylers houſe haunted he</l>
            <l>To woo his prety wife certain</l>
            <l>and thither I ſhall him bring again</l>
            <l>And there vpright I ſhall him ſet</l>
            <l>that no man ſhall it knowe or wit</l>
            <l>And then euery man wil ſain</l>
            <l>That the Tayler hath him ſlain</l>
            <l>For he was very angry with him</l>
            <l>That he came to his wife ſo oft time</l>
            <l>Of his counſail he was wel appaid</l>
            <l>and his man took vp dane Hew that braid</l>
            <l>And ſet him at the Taylers door anon</l>
            <l>and ran home as faſt as he might gone</l>
            <l>The Tayler and his wife were in bed</l>
            <l>And of Dane Hew were ſore afraid</l>
            <l>Leſt that he would them bewray</l>
            <l>and to his wife began to ſay</l>
            <l>All this night I haue dreamed of this falſe caitife</l>
            <l>that he came to our door (quoth he to his wife)</l>
            <l>Ieſus (quoth his wife) what man be ye</l>
            <l>That of a dead man ſo ſore afraid ye be?</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19652:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
For me thought that you did him ſlo</l>
            <l>With that the Tayler to the door gan go</l>
            <l>And a Polax in his hand</l>
            <l>and ſaw the Munk by the door ſtand</l>
            <l>Whereof he was ſore afraid</l>
            <l>And ſtil he ſtood and no woord ſaid</l>
            <l>Til he ſpake vnto his wife</l>
            <l>Dame now haue I loſt my life</l>
            <l>Without I kil him firſt of all</l>
            <l>Foorth he took his Polax or mall</l>
            <l>And hit Dane Hew vpon the head</l>
            <l>that he fel down ſtark dead</l>
            <l>And thus was Dane Hew three times ſlain</l>
            <l>And yet he wrought him a train</l>
            <l>Alas quoth the Taylers wife</l>
            <l>This caitife dooth vs much ſtrife</l>
            <l>Dame he ſaid what ſhall we now doo?</l>
            <l>Sir ſhe ſaid ſo mote go</l>
            <l>The Munk in a corner ye ſhall lay</l>
            <l>til to morow before the day</l>
            <l>Then in a Sack ye ſhall him thraſt</l>
            <l>and in the Mil dam ye ſhall him caſt</l>
            <l>I counſail it you for the beſt ſurely</l>
            <l>So the Tayler thought to doo truely</l>
            <l>In the morning he took Dane Hew in a Sack</l>
            <l>And laid him lightly vpon his back</l>
            <l>Vnto the Mil Dam he gan him hye</l>
            <l>and there two theeues he did eſpye</l>
            <l>That fro the Mil came as faſt as they might</l>
            <l>But when of the Tayler they had a ſight</l>
            <l>They were abaſhed very ſore</l>
            <l>For they had thought the miller had come thore</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19652:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
For of him they were ſore afraid</l>
            <l>that the Sack there down they laid</l>
            <l>And went a little aſide I cannot tel where</l>
            <l>And with that the Tayler ſaw the ſack lye there</l>
            <l>Then he looked therin anon</l>
            <l>And he ſaw it was ful of Baron</l>
            <l>Dane Hew then he laid down there</l>
            <l>And ſo the bacon away did beare</l>
            <l>Til he came home and that was true</l>
            <l>the theeues took vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſack with dane Hew</l>
            <l>And went their way til they came home</l>
            <l>One of the theeues ſaid to his wife anon</l>
            <l>Dame look what is in that ſack I thee pray</l>
            <l>For there is good bacon by my fay</l>
            <l>Therfore make vs good cheer lightly</l>
            <l>the wife ran to the Sack quickly</l>
            <l>And when ſhe had the Sack vnbound</l>
            <l>the dead Munck therein ſhe found</l>
            <l>Then ſhe cryed out and ſaid alas</l>
            <l>I ſee heer a meruailous caſe</l>
            <l>That ye haue ſlain Dane Hew ſo ſoon</l>
            <l>Hanged ſhall ye be if it be knowen</l>
            <l>Nay good dame ſaid they again to her</l>
            <l>For it hath been the falſe miller</l>
            <l>Then they took Dane Hew again</l>
            <l>and brought him to the mil certain</l>
            <l>Where they did ſteale the Bacon before</l>
            <l>And there they ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged Dane Hew for ſtore</l>
            <l>Thus was he once hanged in deed</l>
            <l>and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> theeues ran ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e as faſt as they could ſpeed</l>
            <l>The Millers wife roſe on the morning erly</l>
            <l>And lightly made her ſelf redy</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19652:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
To fetch ſome Bacon at the laſt</l>
            <l>But when ſhe looked vp ſhe was a gaſt</l>
            <l>That ſhe ſaw the Munk hang there</l>
            <l>She cryed out and put them all in fere</l>
            <l>And ſaid heer is a chaunce for the nones</l>
            <l>for heer hangeth the falſe Munk by cocks bones</l>
            <l>That hath been ſo Lecherous many a day</l>
            <l>And with mens wiues vſed to play</l>
            <l>Now ſome body hath quit his meed ful wel</l>
            <l>I trow it was the Deuil of Hel</l>
            <l>And our Bacon is ſtolne away</l>
            <l>this I call a ſhrewd play</l>
            <l>I wot not what we ſhall this winter eate</l>
            <l>What wife (quoth the Miller) ye muſt all this for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>get</l>
            <l>And giue me ſome good counſail I pray</l>
            <l>How we ſhall this Munk conuay</l>
            <l>And priuily of him we may be quit</l>
            <l>Sir ſhe ſaid that ſhall you lightly wit</l>
            <l>Lay him in a corner til it be night</l>
            <l>and we ſhall conuay him or it be day light</l>
            <l>The Abbot hath a cloſe heer beſide</l>
            <l>therin he hath a good horſe vntide</l>
            <l>Go and fetch him home at night</l>
            <l>and bring him vnto me ſtraight</l>
            <l>And we ſhall ſet him there vpon in deed</l>
            <l>and binde him faſt ſo God me ſpeed</l>
            <l>And giue him a long pole in his hand</l>
            <l>Like as he would his enmies withſtand</l>
            <l>And vnder his-arme we wil it thruſt</l>
            <l>Like as he would fiercely iuſt</l>
            <l>Fo (ſhe ſaid) as ye wel knowe</l>
            <l>the Abbot hath a Mare gentle and lowe</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19652:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
Which ambleth wel and trotteth in no wiſe</l>
            <l>But in the morning when the Abbot dooth riſe</l>
            <l>He commaundeth his mare to him to be brought</l>
            <l>For to ſee his workmen if they lack ought</l>
            <l>And vpon the mare he rideth as I you tel</l>
            <l>For to ſee and all things be wel</l>
            <l>And when this Horſe ſeeth this mare anon</l>
            <l>Vnto her he wil lightly run or gone</l>
            <l>When the Miller this vnderſtood</l>
            <l>He thought his wiues counſail was good</l>
            <l>And held him wel therwith content</l>
            <l>and ran for the horſe verament</l>
            <l>And when he the horſe had fet at the laſt</l>
            <l>Dane Hew vpon his back he caſt</l>
            <l>And bound him to the horſe ful ſure</l>
            <l>that he might the better indure</l>
            <l>To ride as faſt as they might ren</l>
            <l>Now ſhall ye knowe how the Miller did then</l>
            <l>He tooke the horſe by the brydle anon</l>
            <l>and Dane Hew ſitting therdn</l>
            <l>And brought him that of the mare he had a ſight</l>
            <l>Then the horſe ran ful right</l>
            <l>The Abbot looked a little him beſide</l>
            <l>and ſaw that Dane Hew towarde him gan ride</l>
            <l>And was almoſte out of his minde for feare</l>
            <l>When he ſaw Dane Hew come ſo neere</l>
            <l>He cryed help / for the looue of the trinite</l>
            <l>For I ſee wel that Dane Hew auenged wil be</l>
            <l>Alas I am but a dead man</l>
            <l>and with that from his Mare he ran</l>
            <l>The abbots men ran on Dane Hew quickly</l>
            <l>and gaue him many ſtrokes lightly</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:19652:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
With Clubs and ſtaues many one</l>
            <l>They caſt him to the earth anone</l>
            <l>So they killed him once again</l>
            <l>thus was he once hanged and foure times ſlain</l>
            <l>And buried at the laſt as it was beſt</l>
            <l>I pray God ſend vs all good reſt.</l>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don at the long Shop adioyning vnto Saint Mildreds Churche in the Pultrie, by Iohn Allde.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19652:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
